[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Nineteen]
[第十九集]
I see.
我知道
Everyone here.
在座的诸位
Aspiring to be a journalist.
有志于成为一名记者
Then I'll ask for advice. .
那我要请教了
Today's society.
当今社会
To be a qualified journalist.
要成为一名合格的记者
What basic qualities are needed? .
需要哪些基本素质
Please speak freely.
请畅所欲言
I'm all ears.
我洗耳恭听啊
I think the most important thing is.
我认为最重要的是
objective.
客观
I think it is.
我觉得是
learned.
博学
You must dare to tell the truth.
必须要敢说真话
ladies and gentlemen.
诸位
I am interested in the future.
我是有志于将来
Want to run a newspaper like Mr. Shao .
要像邵先生一样去办报的
China today.
当今中国
I think.
我认为
It's a great time for ideas to converge.
是一个思想汇集的大时代
Do a good job.
要办好报
Be a qualified journalist.
做一名及格的新闻记者
The most important quality.
最重要的素质
Is erudition.
便是博学
Ancient and modern Chinese and foreign.
古今中外的
Literature and religion.
历史 文学 宗教
Philosophical geography.
哲学 天文 地理
Even the local conditions and customs of various countries.
甚至于各国各地的风土人情
If they can be integrated.
如果都能融会贯通
Can know everything.
都能无所不晓
Even if you know a thing or two.
哪怕是做到略知一二
Only in this way can you catch useful news.
这样你才能捕捉到有用的新闻
Write a good article.
写出好的文章
The reason why I went from Nanhai, Guangdong.
我之所以从广东南海
Come to Peking University to study.
来北大求学
Just want to rely on.
便是想依靠
The highest institution of higher learning.
这所最高的学府
Get ancient and modern, Chinese and foreign.
获取古今中外
All the knowledge.
所有的知识
Follow Mr Shao's example in the future.
将来效仿邵先生
Be an excellent newspaper man.
做一个优秀的报人
For the Chinese newspaper industry.
为中国的报业
do one's bit.
尽一份力
I don't think he's right. .
我觉得他说得不对呀
Hagen Troy Tan classmate.
陈俊达同学
What you said just now is very good. .
你刚才说得很好
But a little bit. .
但是呢有一点
I beg to differ.
我不敢苟同
That's what you just said.
那就是你刚才说
Want to be a qualified journalist.
想要成为一名合格的新闻记者
First, go to college.
首先要上大学
Even be worthy of.
甚至得上
A school like Peking University .
北京大学这样的学校
To be a qualified journalist.
才能够成为一名合格的记者
Is that what you mean?
你是这个意思吗
Zhongxia classmate.
中夏同学
Isn't that what it is? .
这不正是如此吗
Now we in China.
现如今咱们中国
Is it full of pounds?
是不是充斥了
Too many tabloid reporters.
太多滥竿充数的小报记者
This is precisely the sorrow of China's newspaper industry.
这恰恰是我国报业的悲哀啊
Good!
好啊
So the other students.
那么其他的同学
For member Chen.
对于陈会员
What's the idea of this view?
这个观点有什么想法
The student.
这位同学
You have the floor.
请你发言
Yes, sir.
先生好
I don't agree with this classmate's point of view.
我不赞同这位同学的观点
At least his views are not comprehensive enough.
至少他的观点不够全面
I think today's times.
我认为当今时代
Be a good journalist.
要做好一名新闻记者
Knowledge is important. .
知识博学固然重要
But it is not the only one.
但并不是唯一的
Is not even the most important basic element. .
甚至并不是最重要的基本要素
And!
而且呀
This knowledge is not necessarily.
这知识不一定
Completely from school education.
完全来自于学校的教育
Society is also a university.
社会也是个大学嘛
So I think ...
所以我认为
Be an excellent journalist.
要做一名出色的记者
More important than knowledge.
比知识更重要的
Is the human mind.
就是人的思想
Position and professional ethics.
立场还有职业操守
good.
好
Please be more specific.
请你说得具体一点
I think.
我觉得
As a journalist.
作为一名新闻记者
Can't follow others' advice.
不能人云亦云
The information you want to get for yourself.
要对自己获取的信息
analytic demonstration.
分析 论证
discard what is false and keep what is genuine.
去伪存真
from the surface to the centre.
由表及里
Make your own judgment and conclusion.
做出自己的判断与结论
of course.
当然
The position here is crucial.
这里面立场是至关重要的
We have to stand in the position of the masses. .
我们只有站在大众的立场上
Stand in front of the historical trend.
站在历史潮流的前面
Safeguard the interests and demands of most people.
维护大多数人的利益和要求
Our article.
我们的文章
Is conducive to the progress of this society. .
才有助于这个社会的进步
definitely.
当然啦
Want to be a reporter.
要想做一名记者
First of all, we must strictly abide by professional ethics.
首先要严格地遵守职业操守
Follow the objectivity and authenticity of news.
遵循新闻的客观性真实性
Strive to adhere to the truth.
努力地坚持真理
Insist on seeking truth from facts.
坚持实事求是
Consciously reject the temptation and pollution of interests.
自觉地拒绝利益的诱惑和污染
We are now in troubled times.
我们现在身处乱世
Conduct is the most important thing.
操守品行才至关重要
Good point!
说得好
Fair enough. That's right.
说得对
That's good.
说得不错
Chen member.
陈会员
Speech to your classmate.
你对这位同学的发言
What do you think?
有什么看法
I'd love to hear your argument.
我很想听听你的辩论
Dear Mr Shao.
尊敬的邵先生
ladies and gentlemen.
诸位
I just want to remind you. .
我只想提醒各位一句
The student.
这位同学
Is not an official member of our research institute.
并不是我们研究会的正式会员
He's just.
他仅仅是
An assistant in our Peking University library.
我们北大图书馆的一名助理员
Don't you just.
难道大家就
let it be .
算了
For her point of view.
对于他的观点
I am unable and unwilling to comment.
我无法并且不愿意去评论
How did you! It's not impressive.
你怎么瞧不起人啊
That's too much to say .
这么说太过分了
How can you say that?
怎么能这么说呢
Isn't this unbearable?
这不是焦不起人吗
Look down on people.
看不起人嘛
Your speech just now.
你刚才的讲话
Makes me very sad.
让我非常地难过
how.
怎么
Do you think.
难道你以为
You are a student of Peking University.
你一个北大的学生
Is it more noble than a library assistant? .
就比一个图书馆的助理员高贵吗
exactly.
就是
Will princes and princes have seed? .
王侯将相宁有种乎
You should know the truth of this sentence.
这句话的道理你应该清楚
But I don't think you are a prince. .
可是我看你既不是王侯
Nor is it a leader.
也不是将相
How do you know that classmate Mao Zedong.
你怎么就知道毛泽东同学
Is not our member?
就不是我们的会员呢
In my opinion.
依我看
Mazedong's Cognition of Journalism.
毛泽东对新闻学的认知
As good as you, a philosophy student at Peking University.
不比你这个北大哲学门的学生差
I finished.
我讲完了
nicely.
好 好
good.
好
Yuanmin.
畅快淋漓
So you are Mao Zedong, a 28-year-old painter.
原来你就是二十八画生毛泽东啊
sir.
先生
Yes.
是的
Mr. Yang Changji recommended you to me many times.
杨昌济先生向我推荐你很多次了
I also read your article.
我还看过你的文章
Research on Physical Education.
《体育之研究》
right.
对吧
I'm inspired.
我很受启发
毛泽东.
毛泽东
I am very happy.
我很高兴
We have members like you in our news research society.
我们新闻研究会有你这样的会员
I'd like to welcome you to Beijing Daily.
我欢迎你到 《京报》 经常来坐坐
Where can we communicate?
咱们哪交流交流
sit.
坐
Okay, let's start the next topic. .
好 我们开始下一个课题
润之.
润之
come on.
来来来
you see.
你看
This is our editorial office.
这几就是我们的编辑室
Hello, Mr Shao.
邵先生好
good.
好
It's crude. Don't take it amiss.
很简陋啊 不要见怪
Make yourself at home and make yourself at home.
你呢不要拘束 随便一点
润之.
润之
What are you thinking?
在想什么呢
Iron-shouldered hand.
铁肩辣手
Tiedan Daoyi.
铁肩担道义
Write a hot article.
辣手著文章
sir.
先生
I learned from this hot word.
我从这个辣字
can see.
可以看到
Your persistence in truth.
您对真理的执着
And adherence to faith.
和对信仰的坚守
good.
好
You speak very well.
你说得很好
These four words.
这四个字
Is my view of news.
就是我的新闻观
At the same time I think .
同时我认为
As a journalist, you should have such ethics.
作为记者就应该有这样的操守
润之啊.
润之啊
We must do justice.
我们一定要伸张正义
Advocating ideas.
崇尚思想
At the same time?
同时呢
Or fear life and death to awaken the people.
要不惧生死 去唤醒民众
This is our integrity and character.
这才是我们的操守和品性
sir.
先生
Your character.
您的品性
Students are taught.
学生受教了
be out of the question.
谈不上
I am today.
我今天啊
I'm not talking to you about ethics.
不是跟你谈什么操守的
I just want to exchange ideas with you.
只想跟你交流一下思想
I need you to come with me .
你跟我来
Sit casually.
随便坐
I have prepared excellent tea for you.
我给你准备了上好的茶叶
What about today?
咱们今天呢
Bianpin tea.
一边品茶
Side to side.
一边交心
be it so.
好吧
润之.
润之
You said earlier.
之前你说
A reporter.
一个记者
Should have his position and thoughts.
应该有他的立场和思想
This is particularly important.
这特别重要
I am deeply impressed.
我深以为然
so.
所以
I want to ask.
我想问一下
You recently.
你最近
Do you read any books?
有看什么书吗
Have no ideas of their own.
有没有自己信奉的思想
sir.
先生
I am usually in Changsha.
我平时在长沙
It is rare to see any new books.
很少能看到什么新的书籍
so.
所以
As long as I can find it.
只要我能找到的
I'll watch them all.
我全都看
As for what kind of new ideas to believe in.
至于信奉什么样的新思想
Not yet.
还谈不上
But relatively speaking.
不过相对而言
At this stage.
在这个阶段
I'm against anarchism.
我对无政府主义
More impressive.
印象更深刻一些
anarchism.
嗯
I had a good feeling for it before. .
我之前也对它很有好感
Especially Krupotkin's mutual aid theory.
尤其是克鲁泡特金的互助论
But in the past year.
但是过去一年
I'm interested in socialism.
我对社会主义
Have a strong interest.
产生了浓厚的兴趣
润之.
润之
Did you know that last year.
你知不知道在去年
The revolution in our country.
俄国发生的革命
I've heard of it.
我听说过
This time to Beijing.
这次到北京
I often listen to Mr. Shouchang and Mr. Zhongfu.
我常听守常先生和仲甫先生提
Then I went to the library to check the information.
后来又到图书馆查了资料
But it's all bits and pieces.
但是都是零零碎碎的
No concrete system has been formed yet.
还没有形成什么具体的体系
寿昌先生.
守常先生
I see.
我知道
He is studying Marx's historical materialism.
他正在研究马克思的唯物史观
I was also influenced by him.
我也是受了他的影响
Just started to contact socialism.
才开始接触社会主义的
it suddenly occurs to me that.
对了
These materials.
这些资料
It's about Marxism.
是关于马克思主义
And the Russian revolution.
和俄国革命的
Take a look.
你看一下
I'm inspired.
我很受启发
sit.
坐
What about me?
我呢
It will take some time.
会找一段时间
Put these.
把这些呀
Go through it all again.
都重新梳理一遍
Publish two books.
出两本书
It's called A Comprehensive Study of Social Thoughts in Various Countries.
一本叫《综合研究各国社会思潮》
Where's the other one?
另外一本呢
It's called The Study of New Russia.
叫《新俄国之研究》
i believe.
我相信
As long as these two books are published.
只要这两本书出了
Will definitely give it to the Chinese ideological circle.
一定会给中国的思想界
Bring a new breath of air.
带来一股新的空气
润之.
润之
This world.
这个世界
Is developing rapidly.
在飞速地发展
We work in journalism.
我们搞新闻工作的
Can't lag.
不能滞后
We must keep up closely.
我们一定要紧紧地跟上
The pace of this era.
这个时代的步伐
sir.
先生
I will.
我以后
Can I often come to you for advice? .
可以经常过来向您讨教吗
润之.
润之
The Gate of Beijing News.
《京报》 的大门
To you forever.
永远向你敬开
eh.
嗯
Years later.
多年后
Mazedong told American journalists.
毛泽东对美国记者
Edgar snow said.
埃德加·斯诺说
Shao Fengping helped me a lot.
邵飘萍对我帮助很大
He is a lecturer at the Press Society. .
他是新闻学会的讲师
A liberal.
一个自由主义者
A passionate ideal.
一个具有热情理想
And people of good quality.
和优良品质的人
who.
哪位
Good news for people.
孑民 好消息
Germany surrendered.
德国投降了
We won.
我们胜利了
Brother Tang, you are really a dragon and a horse spirit.
伯棠兄 你真是龙马精神
The victory of the European War was expected.
欧战胜利早是预料中的事情啊
I don't need you either.
也用不着你
Call in the middle of the night.
半夜三更地打电话
Come and wake me up.
来把我吵醒了呀
Man, it's been almost eighty years.
孑民老弟呀 快八十年了
China became a victorious country for the first time.
中国第一次成了战胜国
Can you still sleep?
你还睡得着觉啊
Such a victorious country.
这样的战胜国
is it interesting.
有意思吗
Is it worth celebrating?
值得庆贺吗
Whatever they think.
管他们怎么想呢
To defeat a country is to defeat jade. .
战胜国就是战胜国
You're not happy yourself.
你自己都不高兴
Can somebody else make you happy?
人家能让你高兴吗
People, bro.
孑民老弟啊
How many years?
多少年了
But we can finally hold our heads high for once.
我们可是终于能扬眉吐气一回了
Be sure to celebrate with great fanfare.
一定要大张旗鼓地庆祝一番
Thank you, Brother Botang, for your inspiration. .
多谢伯棠兄的点拨
I see.
我知道
It should be celebrated.
是应该好好地庆贺一番
In 1918.
一九一八年
World War I.
第一次世界大战
End with the victory of the allies over the allies.
以协约国战胜同盟国而宣告结束
China has become a victorious country.
中国成为战胜国
The news came that the whole country was crazy. .
消息传来 举国若狂
Immerse yourself in the triumph of justice over power.
沉浸在公理战胜强权
Happy people.
喜悦中的人们
Cleander Monument, a symbol of shame .
将象征耻辱的克林德碑
Renamed the monument to victory over justice.
改名为公理战胜碑
Li Dazhao published during this period.
李大钊在此期间发表了
Victory of Bolshevism.
《布尔什维主义的胜利》
New Era and other articles.
《新纪元》等文章
And published in Central Park.
并在中央公园发表
Speech.
题为《庶民的胜利》的演说
Pointing out the victory of this war .
指出取得这次战争胜利的
Not the force of the Allies.
不是协约国的武力
But the new spirit of the human world.
而是人类世界的新精神
Is the people of the world.
是全世界的庶民
"The Victory of the People" and other articles.
《庶民的胜利》等文章
It's Li Dazhao who promotes Marxism.
是李大钊宣传马克思主义
And the important documents of the October Revolution in Russia.
和俄国十月革命的重要文献
It shows that he has formed.
表明他已经形成了
Marxist stand and viewpoint.
马克思主义的立场和观点
Promoted the spread of Marxism in China.
促进了马克思主义在中国的传播
Fellow citizens.
同胞们
since.
自从
Germany lost the battle. .
德国打了败仗
Righteousness conquers power. .
公理战胜强权这句话
Almost everyone's mantra.
几乎成了人人的口头禅
Then you know what justice is.
[李大钊 字 守常 北京大学图书馆主任]
What is power?
什么是强权吗
to be short.
简单地说
Everyone who is equal and free.
凡合乎平等自由的
Is justice.
就是公理
long.
倚仗自身强力
Infringe on the equality and freedom of others.
侵害他人平等自由的
Is power.
就是强权
1 Germany relies on its academic excellence.
德国 倚仗它的学问好
Strong strength.
兵力强
Infringe on the equality and freedom of all countries.
专门侵害各国的平等自由
now.
如今
It was badly beaten.
它打得大败
This is the triumph of justice over power.
这就是公理战胜强权
The result of this axiom defeating power.
这公理战胜强权的结果
People all over the world should understand.
世界各国的人都应该明白
Both internally and externally .
无论对内对外
Power is unreliable.
强权是靠不住的
Justice is absolutely indispensable.
公理是万万不能不讲的了
good.
好
Next, please welcome the president of Peking University.
接下来 有请我们北大的校长
Mr Cai Yuanpei delivered a speech.
蔡元培先生 发表演讲
good.
好
Fellow countrymen and classmates.
同胞们 同学们
The disastrous world war is over.
灾难深重的世界大战结束了
The allies won.
协约国获得了胜利
This victory is hard to come by.
这个胜利来之不易啊
We will ride the east wind.
我们要乘着这个东风
Put the unequal darkness in the world.
把世界上不平等的黑暗主义
Destroy.
消灭掉
Use Illuminatism.
用光明主义
Replace it.
取代它
Okay, okay, okay.
好 好 好
I hope that there is a power theory in China.
我希望 国内持强权论的
Believing in dogmatism.
崇拜武断主义的
To plot and cling to prejudice.
好弄阴谋 执着偏见
We must give up this kind of darkness quickly.
都要赶快放弃这种黑暗主义
Make efforts for the bright future of China.
为中国的光明做出努力
Expel power and welcome light.
驱逐强权 迎接光明
nicely.
好 好
Fellow citizens.
同胞们
We are celebrating victory in recent days.
最近几天我们在庆祝战胜
It's very lively.
很是热闹啊
But I want to ask a question.
但是我想问一个问题
Which one did we defeat?
我们战胜的究竟是哪一个
We celebrated.
我们庆祝的
Which one are you celebrating for?
究竟又是为了哪一个而庆祝呢
I honestly say a fair word.
我老老实实地讲一句公道话
This victory is by no means the force of the United Nations. .
这次战胜的绝不是联合国家的武力
But the new spirit of mankind all over the world. .
而是全世界人类的新精神
This time, it is not any country that has been defeated.
这次战胜的 也不是哪一个国家
Or the politics of warlords or capitalists.
军阀或者资本家的政治
But the people of the world.
而是世界的庭民
We celebrated.
我们庆祝的
And it's not for any country.
也不是为了哪一个国家
Or a part of a country. .
或者哪一个国家的一部分人而庆祝
It's a celebration for people all over the world. .
是为了全世界的庭民而庆祝
We are not celebrating to defeat Germany. .
我们不是为了战胜德国而庆祝
But to defeat the militarism of the world.
而是为了打败了世界的军国主义
And celebrate.
而庆祝
Okay, okay, okay.
好 好 好
Fellow countrymen and classmates.
同胞们 同学们
Today among you.
今天在你们当中
Come a lot.
来了很多
Workers brothers in Xindian.
长辛店的劳工兄弟们
I want to say a word to you. .
我要跟大家讲一句话
Notice of the future world.
须知今后的世界
To become a world of labor.
要变成劳工的世界
We should use this trend. .
我们应当用此潮流
Make everything everyone.
使一切人人
The opportunity to become workers.
都变成工人的机会
This trend should not be used.
不应该用此潮流
Make everything everyone.
使一切人人
The chance to become robbers.
都变成强盗的机会
Anyone who doesn't work for nothing.
凡是不做工 吃干饭的
Are robbers.
都是强盗
Robbers and robbers.
强盗和强盗
Seek illegitimate property.
谋取不正的财产
That's also a robber.
那也是强盗
It makes no difference.
没有什么分别
So I want to say .
所以我要说
labour.
劳工
long live.
万岁
Long live the labor, long live the labor.
劳工万岁 劳工万岁 劳工万岁
Let me tell you two.
我告诉二位
Attend this rally today. .
今天参加这个集会呀
I have a new perception.
我有一种新的感知
I feel our new culture movement.
我感觉到我们新文化运动啊
Has reached a new turning point. .
已经到了一个新的转折点
Of course, I still feel very dirty.
当然我这种感觉还是很朦胧的
What about the past.
过去呢
We are always in the study on campus.
我们总是在校园里 书斋里
Wenrenduili.
文人堆里
Today, we came to the society.
今天呢我们来到了社会
Into the public.
走进了大众
I feel heaven and earth.
我感觉到天地呀
All of a sudden it widened.
一下子宽阔了起来
Cai Gong, you feel so right.
蔡公 你感觉太对了
I feel the same way with you.
我跟你有同感
When I heard Shouchang shout out.
当我听到守常喊出
Long live the labor.
劳工万岁的时候
I got goose bumps all over.
我起了一身鸡皮疙瘩
It's like seeing a new world.
好像看到了新的世界
Found new vitality.
找到了新的活力
Brother Zhongfu goes to the public.
仲甫兄 走向大众
This is the turning point we are looking for.
这就是我们要寻找的那个转折点
Shouchang, you are good today.
守常你今天不错
That speech of yours.
你那个演讲啊
Make the question clear and accurate.
把问题说得很清楚也很准确
I look!
我看哪
Not only do you want to be the director of Peking University Library? .
你不光是要做北大图书馆的主任
You will also be a professor at Peking University. .
你还要兼做北大的教授
You are in the propaganda and agitation of the masses .
你在宣传和鼓动群众方面
You are better than Zhongfu Shizhi and all of them.
你比仲甫 适之他们都强
You flatter me.
您过奖了
寿昌还提出.
守常还提出
Outside "New Youth".
在《新青年》之外
Run another Weekly Review.
再办一个《每周评论》
Commenting on current affairs and politics, mobilizing people.
专门评论时事政治 发动民众
I think it should be put on the agenda.
我觉得应该提上日程了
中富啊.
仲甫啊
"New Youth" is not only to be done.
《新青年》不光要办
Weekly review.
《每周评论》
We should put the strength of all teachers and students in Peking University.
我们要把全北大师生的力量
Mobilize.
整合动员起来
Take advantage of the victory of the European war. .
借着欧战胜利这股东风
The fire that awakens my Chinese culture .
把我中华文化觉醒之火啊
Burn up while you can.
趁势烧起来
Ok, let's arrange the meeting when we go back to our liberal arts department.
好 回去我们文科就开会布置
Your country has arrived.
诸位 国运来了
Zhou Li should be restored.
周礼就该恢复啊
My old inspiration has also come.
老夫的灵感也来了
Look, this is a new novel written by the old lady.
你们看 这是老夫新写的小说
Jingsheng and Demon Dream.
《荆生》和《妖梦》
I want to ride the east wind of victory in the European war. .
我要乘着欧战胜利的东风
Jiang Cai Yuanpei Chen Duxiu.
将蔡元培 陈独秀
Hu Qian Xuantong.
胡适 钱玄同
These deviant demon engines.
这帮离经叛道的妖擎
Go to the moral court.
送上道德法庭
What the teacher said is right.
恩师所言甚是啊
Lin Gong!
林纾公啊
Look at this.
您看看这个
This is what I wrote for our magazine National Heritage.
这是我为我们杂志 《国故》
Write the publication of.
撰写的发刊词
Look at this sentence.
您看这句
The national enemy is to awaken our generation and refresh Yan Gang.
国故者 就是唤醒我辈刷新颓纲
Blowing dust.
扇起游尘
Save people with lofty ideals.
挽救斯文之有志之士
Heli encircles the nest Chen Duxiu Hu Shi, etc.
合力围剿陈独秀 胡适等
Forget the ancestors, mess with the country and spoil the customs.
数典忘祖 乱国坏俗的馋慝
nicely.
好 好
Open the door with a clear-cut stand.
开宗明义 旗帜鲜明 直捣黄龙
good.
好
Uncle Shen, come and have a look. .
申叔兄 你也来看看
come.
来
They are all colleagues in the same institution of higher learning.
都是一个学府里共事的同人
You're naming names like this, and you're falling out.
你这样指名点姓 撕破脸皮
Right.
合适吗
What's more, the funds of "National Heritage".
更何况 这《国故》的经费
Or approved by Zhongfu.
还是仲甫批的
Uncle Shen, you are too soft-hearted.
申叔兄 你太过妇人之仁了
Then Chen Duxiu is Cai Yuanpei.
那陈独秀就是蔡元培
Got a big cancer for Peking University.
给北大弄来的一个大毒瘤
Do not eradicate it.
不将之铲除
There is no peaceful day in Peking University.
北大无宁日
Uncle Shen.
申叔啊
I don't think you should treat that Chen Duxiu.
我看你就不要对那个陈独秀
Have any illusions?
抱什么幻想了
Let me tell you.
我告诉大家
Peking University will soon cancel the senior system.
北大很快就要取消学长制了
And Chen Duxiu, a liberal arts senior,.
而陈独秀这个文科学长
No energy consumption till summer vacation. .
能不能耗到暑假
It's hard to say. .
还很难说呢
It is said that Tom and Shen Yinmo.
据说汤尔和 沈尹默
These people are in front of Cai Yuanpei.
这些人在蔡元培面前
I haven't given Chen Duxiu less eye drops recently.
近日没少给陈独秀上眼药
It seems that the lineup of their new culture.
看来他们这个新文化的阵容
Has begun to differentiate.
已经开始分化了
exactly.
没错
As far as I know.
据我所知
李大钊跟胡适.
李大钊跟胡适
There is disagreement on many issues.
在很多问题上的看法都不一致
Li Dazhao advocates direct discussion of politics.
李大钊主张直接议论政治
Shi advocates only academic discussion.
胡适主张只谈学术
Okay, great.
好 太好了
The opportunity has finally come.
机会终于来了
Masters are making academic challenges.
各位大师在学术上发难
I use my knife in politics.
我在政治上动刀
Teacher, I will submit a bill to Congress tomorrow.
恩师 明天我就向国会提交议案
Black Cai Yuanpei, the president of Peking University. .
罢免蔡元培这个北大校长
驱逐陈独秀.
驱逐陈独秀
nicely.
好 好
I declare that I am brilliant.
我声明 我辜鸿铭
Never do anything to destroy Mr Cai Yuanpei.
绝不做低毁蔡元培先生的事情
I'm sorry to leave now.
对不起 告辞了
I'm leaving now, too.
我也告辞了
Uncle Shen.
申叔兄
Shenshu.
申叔
What a cliche!
好 真是腐儒
I was just laughing at people's differentiation.
刚刚还在笑话人家分化哪
As a result, I broke up first.
结果呢 自己倒先散伙了
my kind and respected master/teacher/mentor.
恩师
Teacher, don't worry. .
恩师别急 莫急
I'm in no hurry and I'm not afraid. .
我不急 我也不怕
I'm Zhong Kui the ghost hunter.
我就是打鬼的钟馗
I'm just going to be with them.
我就是要和他们这群人
fight to the end.
战斗到底
After the victory of the European War.
这个欧战胜利后啊
It's like the enthusiasm of our Chinese people.
好像我们中国人的那种热情啊
It was suddenly ignited.
它一下子给点燃了
I don't know if everyone has noticed.
我不知道大家注意没有
It's on this street now.
现在这个街上啊
Those new things.
那些新鲜事啊
There are many.
出现了很多
Peking University is no exception.
我们北大也不例外
Less than a month's time.
一个多月不到的时间
Twenty kinds of newspapers and magazines associations.
二十多种报刊杂志社团
It came out.
就涌现了出来
There is such an emerging situation in Peking University.
北大出现这样的新兴局面
You want me to say it?
要我说呀
This new culture is the result of its development in Peking University. .
这是新文化在北大开展的结果
So I want to thank Mr. Zhong Geng. .
所以说 我要感谢仲甫先生哪
Sir, you flatter me.
先生 您过奖了
We asked for a research fund from the Ministry of Education.
我们从教育部要了一笔研究经费
It is mainly intended to be earmarked for funding. .
主要是想专项用于资助
Academic research of our liberal arts.
我们文科的学术研究
So encourage teachers and students.
所以就鼓励师生
Run more community magazines.
多办一些社团 杂志
So everyone's enthusiasm.
[夏元瑮 字 浮筠 北京大学理科学长]
It was mobilized.
就被调动起来了
The mushrooming is unstoppable.
雨后春笋 势不可挡
Mr. Cai.
蔡先生
At the beginning, you proposed to run more community publications.
当初您提出要多办些社团刊物
I still have concerns.
我还有所顾虑
Think about Peking University?
认为北大呢
Do not have a broad foundation for academic research.
不具备学术研究的广泛基础
So science didn't move.
所以呢 理科没动
I really regret it now .
现在真是后悔呀
The liberal arts group started to move.
这文科的学团一动起来
The atmosphere of the whole school has changed.
整个学校的风气都变了
That's great.
真是太好了
That's right.
可不是嘛
Before?
以前呢
Our students from Peking University are outside class. .
咱们北大的学生在课外呀
There is neither noble entertainment.
既没有高尚的娱乐
There is no automatic organization.
也没有自动的组织
So what about outside the school? .
所以 学校之外呢
Often engage in some abnormal pastimes.
经常搞一些不正常的消遣
exactly.
没错
But, ah.
不过啊
Since it was recently opened.
自从最近开办了
Since various societies and societies.
各种社团和学会以来
This ethos has greatly changed.
这个风气大大地改观了
Students spontaneously organized together.
同学们自发地组织到一起
I'll never go to that shelter again.
再也不去那三瓦两舍之所了
Ah, this liberal arts is a driving force.
是啊 这文科一带动啊
Students from all subjects followed suit.
各科学生纷纷效仿
Spontaneously set up the association Chinese Literature Society. .
自发成立了社团 国文学会
Society of Historiography and Mathematics.
史学会 数学会
There is also an interdisciplinary calligraphy research society.
还有跨系科性的书法研究会
And so on.
音乐会 等等
Of course, the research is in-depth.
当然了 研究深入了
There are even more controversial issues.
争论的问题也就更多了
What about academic issues?
学术问题呢
It's a mess now.
现在吵得是一塌糊涂
What a joy!
不亦乐乎啊
This is not afraid, this is not afraid.
这不怕 这不怕
This argument is always a good thing.
这个争论呢 向来是好事
I also advocate argument.
我也提倡争论
中富兄.
仲甫兄
I heard that liberal arts magazines.
我听说文科的杂志
There's been some controversy lately, isn't there?
怎么近来有些争论是吧
Our liberal arts side.
我们文科这面
Fu Sinian, who is the main school of Chinese literature.
主要是中国文学门的傅斯年
And English literature.
还有英国文学门的
Wait for a few classmates, Luo Jialun.
罗家伦等几位同学
This magazine, Trendy, was co-founded.
合创的这个杂志《新潮》
And the one from the Student Salvation Association.
还有学生救国会的那个
Xu Luo and other students founded "National".
许德珞等同学创办的《国民》
And Yu Shizhen's "National Heritage".
还有俞士镇等的《国故》
Just these magazines.
就这几本杂志
They have different views.
他们这观点各不相同
The tit-for-tat quarrel is very hot.
针锋相对 吵得十分热市
What about this classmate?
这个同学们呢
He is willing to set up a club to run a magazine.
他愿以创社团办杂志的形式啊
To cultivate their own interests.
来培养自己的兴趣
To make your own remarks.
来发表自己的言论
To promote their own ideas.
来宣传自己的主张
And views on current events.
和对时事的看法
I think this should be advocated.
我觉得这是要提倡的
This is important for how they view current events.
这对于他们如何看待时事
How to Improve Academic Communication.
如何提高学术交流
Cultivate one's sentiment.
陶冶自己的情操
And expand your horizons.
还有扩展自己的视野
Are of great benefit.
都大有好处
On this basis.
就在这个基础之上啊
To improve students' spiritual cultivation.
来提高学生们的精神修养
So I thought.
所以我以为
The more magazine associations, the better.
杂志 书刊 社团 多多益善
So all subjects.
所以各科呀
Open the door and experiment boldly.
广开门路 大胆实验
What I want to tell you is.
我想告诉各位的是
This is just the beginning of Peking University's innovation.
这只是北大革新的一个开始
The reform of the system should continue to keep up.
体制革新要继续跟上去
for example.
比如说
The senior system we are implementing now.
我们现在实行的学长制
It is a transitional one.
它就是一个过渡性的
Temporary system.
临时的体制
What Peking University is doing now is to abolish the door and change the department.
现在北大正在做的是废门改系
Then the senior system will be cancelled soon.
那么学长制也很快就要取消
To set up the Academic Affairs Office.
要成立教务处
To unify the leadership of school teaching.
来统一领导学校的教学
So the science chiefs.
所以各科学长啊
You should be mentally prepared.
你们要做好思想准备呦
I feel a lot of noise.
我觉得动静不小啊
It should be changed. Yeah.
应该改 是啊
All right, let's talk about it here today.
好了 我们今天就讨论到这儿
good.
好
Brother Zhongfu, stay here.
仲甫兄 你留一下
I have something else to discuss with you.
我还有点事跟你商量一下
good.
好
Let's drink some water first.
来先喝点儿水
What I just mentioned about the school innovation.
我刚才提的学校革新的事啊
What do you think?
你有什么看法
If Peking University wants to become a world-class university.
北大要想成为世界一流的大学
That must keep up with the world trend.
那必须要跟上世界潮流
This is the trend.
这是趋势
This senior system really can't become the norm.
这学长制确实不能成为常态
So I very much agree with your reform plan.
所以我非常赞同您的改革方案
Now we have to cancel the senior system.
现在要取消学长制啊
What are you going to do?
你打算怎么办呢
I've been trying my best recently.
我最近正在全力地
Prepare the Weekly Review.
筹备《每周评论》
I think this publication.
我觉得这个刊物
It is a platform for us to go public.
是咱们走向大众的一个平台
I'm looking forward to it.
我对它充满期待
Now it's just me and Shouchang.
现在只有我和守常在搞
Not enough.
人手不够
But I think.
不过我想
if possible.
如果可能的话
I want to focus on this publication.
我想把主要精力放在这个刊物上
中富兄啊.
仲甫兄啊
I have always had a wish.
我呢一直有一个愿望
Just want to write a book.
就是想编写一部
General History of China with academic weight .
具有学术分量的 《中国通史》
I want to come and go.
我想来想去
Only you are the most suitable.
只有你是最合适的
So I want to invite you.
所以我想请你呀
He is also the director of the compilation and fundraising department of Peking University National History Museum.
兼任北大国史馆编募处的主任
To lead the editor of the General History of China. .
来统一领导《中国通史》的编辑
Brother Xian, what do you think? .
贤弟 你意下如何啊
Brother Zimin.
孑民兄
You are dissatisfied.
不满您说
Now I.
我现在
All my interests are in the Weekly Review.
全部的兴趣都在《每周评论》上
I think reality is more important than history.
我认为现实比历史更加紧要
What about this Weekly Review?
这个《每周评论》呢
We can ask Shouchang to excuse me a little more.
可以让守常去多担待一些
Now Shizhi is back.
那现在适之回来了
He can also share some.
他也可以分担一些呀
So Shouchang and Shizhi.
那守常和适之
They have different ideas.
他们俩思路不同
Always arguing.
总是争论
I'm afraid they'll fight again if I'm not careful.
我怕一不留神他们再打起来
In fact nothing.
其实没什么
You're the leader.
有你领衔呢
They can't argue much.
他们争论不到哪儿去
You want me to say it?
要我说呀
Something specific.
一些具体的事
Let the young people do it.
就让年轻人去干了
Do you like it?
你看好不好
Let me talk to Shizhi.
我找适之谈谈看嘛
good.
好
sir.
先生
I'm leaving.
我走了
Sell newspapers.
卖报 卖报
Selling newspaper.
卖报
Hard sister-in-law.
辛苦 嫂子
Yes, sir.
好 谢谢先生
Brother Zhongfu, come and sit here.
仲甫兄 来 这儿坐
Your dining room gets off here.
你们家饭厅在这儿下
Okay.
没事 好
史鸷啊.
适之啊
You have been away from Beijing for less than a month.
你这离京不到一个月
Great changes have taken place in Peking University. .
北大却发生了很大的变化
Student factories in various departments.
各科系的学生
Vigorously set up associations.
大力兴办社团
Intramural publications.
校内刊物
That also appeared several copies at once.
那也一下子出现了好几本
You run New Tide.
[胡适 字 适之 北京大学教授]
Liu Shipei Huang Ni takes some people.
刘师培 黄侃带一些人
Run the "National Heritage".
办了《国故》
These magazines fight.
这几本杂志打架
There was a lot of noise.
吵得不亦乐乎
What "National Heritage"?
什么《国故》啊
I just want to be retro.
就是想复古呗
Just some.
不过就是一些
Therefore, the setting sun of our country is dark. .
故国斜阳的呷吟黑了
Huang Cuo is always holding that recently.
最近黄侃总是拿着那个
The first draft of the publication.
发刊词的初稿
Ask for advice everywhere.
到处征求意见
Actually, it was a demonstration.
实际上 那就是示威
How ah.
怎么样啊
Is it like sitting here in your own yard?
坐这儿像不像自己家院里
be like.
像
Is it cold?
冷不冷啊
No, it's cool.
不冷 没事
You went on to say .
你接着说
Did you say Huang Ni just now?
刚才您说黄侃是吧
I heard they also.
我听说他们还
Scold us both by name.
点名道姓地骂咱们俩
I think they flatter me.
我看他们是高抬我了
Now scold us.
现在骂我们的
It's not just the National Heritage family.
可不光是《国故》一家
Now it's a North-South linkage.
现在是南北联动
Can't be pretty.
来势汹汹 不容小觑呀
Our "New Youth".
咱们《新青年》
Don't you grow up in the midst of abuse?
不就是在骂声当中成长的吗
Are you afraid of being scolded by others, Chen Zhongfu? .
你陈仲甫还怕别人骂吗
It's not enough to be afraid.
光不怕还不行
Fight back!
还要反击呀
no problem.
没问题
I'll write an article.
我这就写文章
Argue with them.
和他们辩论
I just want to discuss it with you. .
我正想跟你商量
The new culture movement should go to the masses.
新文化运动要走向大众
Face the reality.
要直面现实
So I thought.
所以我就想
Outside "New Youth".
在《新青年》之外
Run a weekly review.
办一个 《每周评论》
It's a supplement to New Youth.
算是《新青年》的副刊
What Mr. Cai means is.
蔡先生的意思是
I'd like you to help Shouchang host it.
想请你协助守常来主持
The Weekly Review, right?
《每周评论》是吧
What is the purpose of the Weekly Review?
那《每周评论》的宗旨
What is it?
是什么
Weekly Review and New Youth.
《每周评论》跟《新青年》
Do your job.
各司其职吧
Focus on different.
侧重不同
New Youth focuses on ideological enlightenment.
《新青年》侧重思想启蒙
The Weekly Review focuses on current affairs.
《每周评论》侧重评述时事
Criticize reality.
批评现实
On some political issues, practical issues.
就一些政治问题 现实问题
comment.
发表评论
中富兄.
仲甫兄
You've been saying no politics for 20 years.
你一直说二十年不谈政治
But everything you do.
可是你做的每一件事情
Why are they all involved in politics?
为什么都要和政治牵扯不清呢
史鸷啊.
适之啊
You can't keep clinging to this problem.
你不能老是抓着这个问题不放
Actually, I already said that. .
其实我早就说过了
Not talking about politics does not mean not studying current affairs.
不谈政治不等于不研究时事问题
In that case.
如果那样的话
Then let's do the National Heritage, too.
那我们也办《国故》算了
Brother Zhongfu, you misunderstood me.
仲甫兄 你误解我了
I'm not saying that I don't approve of the Weekly Review. .
我不是说不赞成办《每周评论》
For practical problems.
对于现实问题
I really didn't study it.
我确实是没有研究
And lack of interest.
也缺乏兴趣
I have a lot on my hands right now.
我现在手头上的事真的很多
The first volume of Outline of Chinese Philosophy History.
《中国哲学史大纲》的上卷
It will be published immediately.
马上要出版
Mr Cai made me the director of the English department.
蔡先生让我任了英文系的主任
Fu Sinian pulled me hard again.
傅斯年他们又硬拉着我
I went to New Fashion as a consultant. .
去《新潮》做了顾问
Plus my mentor, Mr Dewey.
再加上我的导师杜威先生
Will soon come to China to give lectures.
马上就要来华讲学
I have to contact many things about him.
他的很多事情我都要去联系
I have to go.
还要去张罗
Okay, okay, I know.
行了行了 我知道
I know you're busy.
我知道你忙
But isn't Shouchang more than you?
可是守常不是比你事情更多吗
Look at him.
你看看他
How many clubs and magazines have you run?
办了多少社团和杂志
Really became the leader of the youth.
真正成了青年的领袖
It's true to be a scholar.
这做学问固然没错
But when the whole country is observing.
但是举国维观之时
Isn't responsibility more important?
责任不是更重要吗
Brother Zhongfu teaches you very well.
仲甫兄 教导极是
I let you down.
我让您失望了
fault.
不是
Don't mind.
别在意
I said this because I thought you were my confidant. .
我是把你当知己才这么说的
I see.
我明白
Why don't you think so?
要不这样您看行不行
during this period.
这段时间
I won't host the Weekly Review.
我就不参加主持《每周评论》了
I must write more articles.
我一定多写文章
After this time, I will take over from Shouchang. .
这段时间过后 我接替守常
how about.
怎么样
Two big professors.
两位大教授
Don't freeze in the yard.
不要在院子里冻着了
One pot is ready.
一品锅做好了
eat rice.
吃饭
Here we go.
可以开始了
ladies and gentlemen.
女士们 先生们
Hold a press conference today.
今日召开记者会
To explain to our friends in the press.
是为了向新闻界的朋友们说明
This trip to Paris.
此次赴巴黎
The itinerary of the delegation attending the peace conference.
参加和会代表团的行程
How many of us can represent China?
我们几个为能代表中国
As the representative of the victorious country.
作为战胜国代表的身份
Go to France to attend the peace conference.
去法国参加和会
And feel extremely honored.
而感到万分地荣幸
Let me introduce it first.
首先 由我来介绍一下
The situation of our delegation .
我们代表团的情况
Our delegation consists of.
我们的代表团成员包括
Secretary representing foreign experts, etc. .
全权代表 外国专家 秘书等
A total of more than 50.
共五十余位
Du Lu Zhengxiang.
鄙人陆征祥
Be the head of the delegation.
担任此次代表团的团长
I won't introduce them here.
在这里就不多加介绍了
Other key members of the delegation include.
代表团其他的主要成员包括
Mr. Hu Weide, Minister to France.
驻法公使胡惟德先生
Mr. Ke Sze Sao, Minister to Britain.
驻英公使施肇基先生
The three of us are plenipotentiaries.
我们三个为全权大使
In addition, Mr. Gu Weijun, Minister to the United States .
此外 驻美公使顾维钧先生
Mr. Wei Chenzu, Ambassador to Belgium.
驻比公使魏宸祖先生
Ambassador plenipotentiary and special committee member.
为全权大使兼专门委员
the other day.
日前
Our Minister Hu Wei Shi.
我们的胡公使 魏公使 施公使
Has gone to Paris to negotiate.
已奔赴巴黎洽谈
And attend the preparatory meeting before the peace conference.
并参加和会召开之前的预备会议
Fellow members of the press.
各位新闻界的同人们
The peace conference held in Paris.
此次在巴黎召开的和会
For me in China.
对我中国来说
Is a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity.
是一个千载难逢的机遇
China needs to use this conference.
我们中国要借助此次大会
Seek a certain degree of fair treatment .
谋取某种程度上的公平待遇
And for half a century.
并对半个世纪以来
The painful consequences suffered by China have been corrected.
中国所遭遇的惨痛后果予以修正
Please ask questions below.
下面请诸君提问
Excuse me, Chief Lu.
请问陆总长
How do you predict the outcome of this meeting?
您对此次会议的结果如何预测
Is the outlook optimistic?
前景是否乐观
Can it really be as you said?
是否真的可以如您所说
But for half a century.
可将半世纪以来
To correct the painful consequences suffered? .
所遭受的惨痛后果予以修正呢
In this big war.
在这次大战中啊
China's victory over the Allies .
中国对协约国的胜和
Made a significant contribution.
做出了不可忽略的贡献
Here I can tell you.
在这里我可以向大家透露
Back in China.
早在中国
Before sending hundreds of thousands of laborers to the war.
输送十几万劳工参战之前
Britain and France promised China.
英法政府就允诺中国
At the post-war peace conference.
在战后的和平会议上
Give China five conference seats.
予以我国五个会议席位
Treat each other as big countries.
以大国相待
So people are full of confidence in this meeting.
所以部人对本次会议充满了信心
good.
好
Excuse me, Chief Lu.
请问陆总长
The proposal submitted by your country to the Peace Conference this time .
贵国此次向和平大会提交的提案
What contents are included?
包括哪些内容
good.
好
Our delegation.
我们代表团
Seven proposals have been prepared this time. .
此次准备了七条议案
Give up the sphere of influence .
一 放弃势力范围
Withdraw foreign troops and patrol officers.
二 撤退外国军队以及巡警
Abolishing foreign post offices and wired telegraph offices.
三 裁撤外国邮局及有线电报机关
4. Cancellation of consular jurisdiction.
四 取消领事裁判权
5. Return the leased land.
五 归还租借地
6. Return the concession .
六 归还租界
Freedom of tariff.
七 关税自由权
good.
好
Dear Chief.
尊敬的总长
We see your proposed bill.
我们看到您所提议的议案
Covers a wide range.
涵盖范围非常广
Do you think that at this meeting.
您认为在此次会议上
Can all these requirements be met?
这些要求都能得到满足吗
I think you may all remember.
我想诸位也许都还记得
A month ago.
一个月前
President Xu ordered.
徐大总统下令
The legacy of the "Xin Chou Treaty".
将《辛丑条约》所遗留的
Cleander monument.
克林德碑
Move from Dongdan to Central Park.
由东单移至中央公园
And plans to rewrite the inscription as follows.
并计划将碑文改写为
Conquer axiom.
公理战胜
You asked me at this conference.
你问我在此次大会上
Will these proposals be passed?
这些提议会不会被通过
I just want to answer.
我只想回答说
Righteousness will triumph over might.
公理必将战胜强权
good.
好
Excuse me, Chief Lu.
请问陆总长
You go to Paris for a meeting.
您去巴黎开会
What about the affairs of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs?
那外交部的事务该如何处理呢
The government of the Republic of China has appointed .
民国政府已经委任
Mr. Chen Zhuan, Vice Minister of Foreign Affairs.
外交部次长陈篆先生
Acting foreign minister.
代理外交总长
same time.
同时
At the same time, the Chinese Foreign Affairs Committee will be established.
同时 将建立中国外交委员会
As the decision-making body of China's diplomacy.
作为中国外交的决策机构
This is the end of today's press conference.
今天的记者招待会到此结束
Thank you all.
谢谢诸位
ok, thanks.
好 谢谢
Thank you very much.
非常感谢
thank you.
谢谢
Chief Lu.
陆总长
Presidential instruction.
总统训示
I just finished a press conference here.
我这刚开完记者招待会
What's wrong with them, Eiko?
他们又出什么幺蛾子
What instructions?
什么指示
This trip to Europe to discuss peace relations with Qin Zhong.
此次赴欧议和 关系綦重
The main seat is the legal diplomacy of the main court.
主座以主正廷法律外交夙著才望
He is specially appointed as a special plenipotentiary ambassador.
特加以委任为专门全权大使
Electricity has been transferred from Minister Gu to Wang Zhengting nearby.
已电由顾公使就近转知王正廷
The appointment order will also be sent to the US Museum. .
其委任令亦寄美馆转交
And hope that the revolution and contact with Lu.
并希陆公转与接洽
I hope to persuade you to serve.
淳劝担任为盼
Xu Shichang.
徐世昌
What's going on here?
这是怎么回事
Didn't the southern government mention it long ago.
南方政府不是早就提过
Do you want to set up your own delegation to attend the peace conference .
要自己成立代表团参加和会吗
Isn't the president not allowed?
大总统不是不允吗
The president had refused.
大总统本来是拒绝
Representatives from the North-South Association.
南北双方协派代表的
But the southern government, Dr. Wang Zhengting .
但是 南方政府王正廷博士
Has arrived in new york.
已经到了纽约
He contacted and convinced the United States himself.
他自己联络并说服了美国
Last night, the United States sent its envoy to China, Rui Enshi.
昨晚美国派驻华公使芮恩施
Put pressure on the president.
向大总统施压
The president nodded his head as a last resort.
大总统迫不得已才点了头
With this appointment.
有了这份任命
Look at foreigners' faces everywhere.
处处看着外国人的脸色行事
What about diplomacy?
还谈什么外交
This.
这个这个
This Lord Masayoshi.
这个王正廷
What is his ranking?
他的排位是怎么样的
It's not clear in the appointment letter.
任命书上没有明确
Chen Zhuan said that it came after you.
陈篆说排在您之后
Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary.
是特命全权大使
A delegation of a country .
一个国家的代表团
There are people from the north and south governments.
竟然有南北两个政府的人
It's bound to be a lot of problems .
注定会问题重重啊
I want to speak to Wang Daran.
我要跟汪大燮通话
Give me a big answer.
给我接注大燮
I noticed President Wilson of the United States.
我注意到了美国总统威尔逊
A speech in Congress.
在国会上的演说
He proposed.
他提出
To make the world peaceful forever.
要想让世界永久和平
A new order has to be established.
得建立一个新秩序
No more old-fashioned diplomacy.
不能再用老套的外交方式
To solve the war problem.
来解决战争问题
The victorious country can't ask for compensation for ceded land.
战胜国不能要求割地赔款
Secret diplomacy should be abolished.
要废除秘密外交
Should pass.
应该通过
An organization that maintains world peace.
建立维护世界和平的组织
To create a new order.
来创立一个新秩序
This 14-point plan builds.
这十四点计划构建了
New International Morality.
新新的国际道德
It seems that right triumphs over power this time.
看来这次的公理战胜强权
It's promising.
大有希望啊
Can justice conquer power?
公理能不能战胜强权
Depends on the Paris Peace Conference.
得看巴黎和会的情况
I heard that the representative of this delegation.
我听说这次代表团的代表
It's Foreign Minister Lu Zhengxiang.
是外交总长陆征祥
I also heard that .
我也听说
Liang Qichao was entrusted by Xu Shichang.
梁启超受了徐世昌的委托
Lobbying in Europe.
正在欧洲游说
Proposal for our Paris Peace Conference and China.
为咱们的巴黎和会中国提案
What about blowing and canvassing.
吹风拉票呢
Ren Gong is full of confidence this time.
梁任公这次倒是信心满满啊
Advocating China everywhere.
到处鼓吹中国
Can last a hundred years of international failure.
可以挽百十年国际之失败
Get a big turn from now on. .
从此获得大翻身
Look at this Mr. Liang. .
我看这位梁先生
It's cute and naive.
是又可爱又天真啊
I guess I didn't eat enough for foreigners.
估计是吃洋人的亏没吃够
Shouchang, I think you are too pessimistic.
守常 我觉得你太悲观了
Paris peace conference will play a leading role.
这巴黎和会起主导作用的
It is the United States, Britain and France.
就是美英法三国呀
Wilson's opinion represents.
威尔逊他的主张就代表了
The common proposition of the United States and Britain .
美英法三国共同的主张
So let me see.
所以我看啊
The situation in China is very good. .
中国形势一片大好
be promising.
大有希望
Shizhi, don't forget.
适之你可别忘了
Behind us.
咱们身后
There's also a Japan that's waiting for you.
还有一个虎视耽耽的日本呢
In front of the United States, Britain and France.
在美英法三国面前
Can Japan still play a leading role? .
它日本还能起主导作用吗
It does not play a leading role.
确实起不到主导作用
But you can't guarantee that the United States, Britain and France.
但是你也不能保证美英法三国
Are standing in the same trench with us.
都跟咱们站在同一个战壕
Brother Zhongfu, what do you think.
仲甫兄你怎么看
I agree with Shizhi.
我同意适之的观点
I have studied a lot of Wilson's speeches.
我研究了很多威尔逊的演讲
I think he is a gentleman. .
我觉得他是个君子
He made two suggestions.
他提出两条建议
Countries are not allowed to take power.
一 不许各国拿强权
To violate the equality and freedom of other countries. .
来侵害别国的平等自由
Governments are not allowed to take power. .
二 不许各国政府拿强权
To violate the equality and freedom of the people. .
来侵害百姓的平等自由
I thought about it.
我琢磨了一下
As long as you do these two things .
只要做到这两点
That justice must triumph over power.
那公理必定战胜强权呀